NYSUT Vice President's office files. 6174/002
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- NYS Coordinating Council for Gifted and Talented 1978-1984 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  Senate Minority Task Force Report: Education of the Gifted Child, May 1979; State Education Department position paper, "Educating the Gifted and Talented in New York State," January 1976; proposal, Gifted and Talented Program, submitted to Commissioner of Education, U.S. Office of Education, Department of Health Education and Welfare, by the NYS Consortium for the Education of Gifted and Talented, April 27, 1977; statement by A. Frederick Goossen, executive director, Assembly Education Committee, to NYS Coordinating Council for the Education of the Gifted/Talented, February 5, 1977; newsletters; correspondence
- Global Education 1982-1995 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  "The Relationship between International Education and American Civic Education," presented by Herb Magidson, vice president, American Federation of Teachers, to Department of Education's Educational Symposium for America's Role in World Affairs, May 26, 1989; progress report to Regents and related correspondence re State Education Department's "Education for a Global Perspective: A Plan for New York State," 1982-83; discussion paper by David Dorn, International Affairs Director, American Federation of Teachers, "Wither Education in the 21st Century: A Background Report for the First World Congress of the Education International," with cover note by author to Cortese, soliciting reaction, November 1995
- Global History 1995-1999 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  Evaluations of State Education Department's draft revision of U.S. history curriculum for grades 7, 8, and 11, 1997-98; "Response to Wall Street Journal article of November 17, 1998 and Elaine Wristley Reed's letter to Roseanne DeFabio [National Council for History Education] regarding United States History and Government Social Studies, grade 11," prepared by Elizabeth Sheffer; related correspondence
- Goals 2000. State Application (Box 8, Folder 49)
  Application by State Education Department to U.S. Department of Education for federal funding under Goals 2000: Educate America Act, June 1994; memo to Commissioner Sobol from vp Cortese critically commenting on application, June 15, 1994
- Goals 2000 State Panel 3/31/00 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  Request for proposal; drafts and related materials; "Regents Task Force on Closing the Performance Gap and Statewide Performance Advisory Council "Statement on Closing the Gaps in Student Performance"; Regents discussion item, "Design for a System for Accountability for Student Success," February 29, 2000
- Good Moral Character 1974-1978 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  Text of Commissioner's Regulations re good moral character (administrative procedures for investigation following conviction of a crime by a licensed teacher). See also: Part 83. Good Moral Character; See also: Tenure. 3020a Disciplinary Hearings; See also: Discipline Meeting (Professional Misconduct) 3/28/89
- Governor Cuomo 1989 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  Message to the Legislature, January 4, 1989
- Governor Pataki 1997 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  Governor's press release, "Governor Pataki's School Tax Relief Plan 'STAR' in Budget: Multi-Year Plan Cuts School Property Taxes, Provides Additional School Aid," July 29, 1997; Associated Press report of Pataki's first State of the State address; excerpt of message re education, n.d.
- Governor's Program Bills 1994 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  Text of several proposals to amend the education law re disciplinary procedures for tenured teachers, charter schools, other issues; memo summarizing bills from NYSUT's perspective; recommended changes by NYSUT
- Grade Inflation 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  "Using Standards and Assessments to Support Student Learning: Alternatives to Grade Retention: A Report to the Chancellor's Committee on Grade Transition Standards," by Linda Darling-Hammond and Beverly Falk, Teachers College, Columbia University, September 1995; NYSUT press release, "Blowing the Whistle on Education's 'Open Secret': Teachers report pressure thwarts drive for higher standards," March 3, 1994; "Highlights on Educational Standards," from the NYSUT survey of presidents of elementary and secondary teacher locals, 1993-94; newspaper clipping. See also: Standards & Assessment
- Graduation Requirements (folder 1 of 2) 1997 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  NSYUT Briefing Bulletin: Summary of the Commissioner's Proposal (9/18/97) on Graduation Requirements; NYSUT Response to the Commissioner's Proposal (9/18/97) on Graduation Requirements, approved by NYSUT Board of Directors September 26, 1997; Commissioner's Report to the Regents re decision on graduation requirements, July 1997; drafts of proposals for discussion
- Graduation Requirements (folder 2 of 2) 1997 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Greenburgh 1996-1999 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  Memo form NYSUT general counsel re Greenburgh No. 11 Federation of Teachers v. Greenburgh No. 11 UFSD, noting PERB decision upholding complaints by union, reinstatement of teachers, December 23, 1996; NYSUT publication, "Justice Ignored: The Children's Village School Board Scandal," June 1, 1999, re union-busting attempts
- Hager Sharp. See: Widmeyer, 2000
- Health Care Reform 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  NYSUT/Metropolitan Life "Long-Term Care Workbook," c. 1993; Q&A sheet re NYSUT long-term care plan; "Some Common Questions about Health Acre Reform," prepared for AFT Executive Council and Program and Policy Council meetings, October 1993; booklet, "Health Security: The President's Health Care Plan," re the Health Security Act of 1993; health care resolution for consideration by AFT Executive Council; handwritten notes
- Health Care Task Force 12/1/93, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  Health Security: The President's Report to the American People, White House Domestic Policy Council (forward by Hillary Rodham Clinton), October 1993; Report of the National Leadership Coalition for Health Care Reform, 1991-93; chart comparing Clinton plan with alternative proposals; New York Times clipping
- High Schools That Work 1998 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  Meeting report prepared by NYSUT associates Pat Flynn and Alice Brody, July 21, 1998; fact sheet re program; outline of goals and key practices
- Hill & Knowlton 8/10/00, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Home Schooling 1986-2000 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  NYSUT Information Bulletin, "Home Schooling," May 1997; Wall Street Journal articles re growth in home schooling, October 6, 1986, and March 5, 1997; related articles; annual counts of children educated at home in NYS, by region, 1980-1994; legal brief: U.S. District Court, Northern District of New York, decision in Blackwelder et al. v. Saufner et al., rejecting challenge to right of school districts to evaluate home instruction to determine whether it meets state standards, including amicus brief by NYSUT and NYS School Boards Association, with NYSUT cover letter, June 22, 1988; National Conference of State Legislators State Legislative Report, "Home Schooling: A Primer for State Legislators," 1988; letter from Louis Grummet, Executive Director of NYS School Boards Association, to Lionel Meno, State Education Department Deputy Commissioner, Elementary and Secondary Education, commenting critically on Meno's proposal to remove requirement that home-schooled students be subject to standardized testing, and letter to Cortese from Grummet, commenting on correspondence, August 15, 1989
- Home Schooling. WABC NY Interview w/ Toni Cortese 8/29/00, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  Talking points and background information
- HOPE (Higher Potential for Education) 1999-2002 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  Memo to NYSUT Board of Directors re negative impact of standardization, demoralizing effect of accountability, background re HOPE as advocacy group opposing higher state academic standards, n.d.; petition opposing "high-stakes" testing; HOPE Teacher Forum report to Commissioner Mills and the Board of Regents, March 21, 2001; related newsletters and newspaper clippings
- Hudson Institute Visions of the Future 1982-1985 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  Activities guide; teacher guide; social science activities text; cover letters
- Hudson Institute Visions of the Future 1984 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  "History and Status Report: The Arizona Experiment: The First Regional Project for Visions of the Future," June 1984; draft contract between NYSUT and Hudson Institute, September 7, 1984; final report, "School-to-Work Transition Programs: A Policy Analysis," prepared for Jobs for America's Graduates, Inc., Washington, D.C., January 1984; related correspondence
- I., Miscellaneous 1988-1995 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  Memo to Toni Cortese and Chuck Santelli re illegal immigrant bill, April 26, 1995, with attached newspaper clipping re bill to end most state-provided benefits; letter from New York State School Boards Association re intergenerational programming (programs for the aging) in New York State, December 7, 1989; meeting materials by Industrial Relations Research Association (IRRA), 1989-89; letters from Antonia Cortese to applicants for executive assistant position, 1988
- Incidental Teaching 1987-1996 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  Proposed regulations of the Commissioner, and comments from NYSUT
- Inclusive Schools 5/5/93, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  AFT Special Information Packet: Student Achievement Data and International Assessments, c. 1992; AFT QuESTline newsletter, "Starting with Standards: The Route to Lasting School Reform," winter 1992; handwritten notes
- International Affairs (folder 1 of 3) 1982-1987 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  AFL-CIO pamphlets of foreign policy; NYSUT pamphlet, "Organized Labor's Foreign Policy: Freedom of Association"; pamphlet, "The AFT and International Affairs"; pamphlet, "The Struggle for Democracy in Central America," cosponsored by AIFLD, Social Democrats USA, and others; booklet, "The Peace Movement and the Soviet Union," by Vladimir Bukovsky, reprinted from Commentary, 1982; remarks of Paul F. Cole, secretary-treasurer, NYS AFL-CIO, at the International Affairs Conference, October 9, 1987; materials from 30th annual National Security Seminar, U.S. Army War College, June 4-8, 1984, including unsigned firsthand report; AFT resolution on the Philippines, February 22, 1986; correspondence; newsletters, including The Pluralist, Democracy International, Falls Church, VA, February 1982; article reprints and newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- International Affairs (folder 2 of 3) 1982-1987 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  Materials re Nicaragua and El Salvador, including Department of State publications; AFL-CIO resolutions; article reprints; and newspaper clippings compiled by NYSUT Office of Public Relations
- International Affairs (folder 3 of 3) 1982-1984 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  Democrats '82: National Party Conference draft workshop statements re foreign policy and security issues; Department of State policy papers and publications, including Realism, Strength, Negotiation: Key Foreign Policy Statements of the Reagan Administration, May 1984; article reprints; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- International Education 1981 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  Clipping summarizing findings by Educational Testing Service noting that education majors had lowest scores on knowledge of international affairs, June 1981; brochures: "The AFT and International Affairs," "A Foreign Policy with a Purpose," by Lane Kirkland, "American Labor's Involvement in World Affairs"; discussion paper by State Education Department, "Education for a Global Perspective: A Plan for New York State"; congressional testimony by AFT on post-secondary education (Paul Simon bill, H.R. 3231), with cover letter to Cortese, August 26, 1981; memo from Cortese to BNYSUT officers outlining proposed NYSUT international education program, August 5, 1981
- International Education Advisory Committee 1/22/83, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  Agenda for NYSUT conference, "Labor's Stake in International Affairs," April 2-14, 1982; Center for Appeals for Freedom Lecture Bureau Speakers 19982-1983
- International Education. AFL-CIO Positions 1981 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  Several issues of AFL-CIO Free Trade Union News; meeting agendas, November 19 and October 27, 1981
- International Education Meeting 7/23/81, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  Letters to Cortese critiquing international education plan, July 1981; handwritten notes
- International Education (folder 1 of 2) 1975-1981 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  Senate testimony by AFT on the Higher Education Act, October 3, 1979; packet of newspaper clippings on El Salvador, 1981; newsletters, policy papers, and article reprints; handwritten notes
- International Education (folder 2 of 2) 1975-1981 (Box 9, Folder 23)
- International Affairs Conference 3/4-3/6/83, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  Conference agenda, "Labor's Stake in International Affairs"; speech (by Cortese?) to conference re NYSUT position; speech by Al Shanker, March 4, 1983; list of invitees; follow-up correspondence, update on activities
- International Education Conference 4/2-4/4/82, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  Handwritten notes; agenda
- International Affairs Conference. Vouchers 1983 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- International Federation of Free Trade Unions (IFFTU) Conference 1984 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  Brochures and newsletters; monthly update bulletin February/March 1984; resolutions re illiteracy and related issues
- IFFTU/UNESCO Survey 1982 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Response to survey, "Participation of Teachers' Unions in Educational Planning," letter to Cortese from AFT re IFFTU survey
- International Teachers Conference to Combat Racism (folder 1 of 2) 1980 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  Tel Aviv, Israel. Printed proceedings; article reprints; cover letter from AFT
- International Teachers Conference to Combat Racism (folder 2 of 2) 1980 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  Unattributed white paper, "The Black Hebrews," c. 1979, and related newspaper clippings; printed publications
- Italian-American Labor Council 1998 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  Letter to vp Cortese thanking her for continued membership
- Japan 1994-1995 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  Draft Report of the AFT Delegation to Japan, with handwritten comments and cover letter to vp Cortese, January 10, 1995; related memos re Japanese education system
- Jewish Labor Committee 1996 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  Letter to Cortese asking her to become member; program highlight sheets
- Joint Decision Making 1989 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  NYSUT draft documents, June 1989: "Guidelines for Agreements on Professional Decision-Making," "Are Your Ready for Joint Decision-Making? An Awareness Instrument," "The Union Role in Joint Decision Making: A Legal and Educational Background," with cover letter to field staff asking for comments; agreement between the Chittenango Teachers Association and the superintendent of the central school district, April 1989; related materials. See also: Shared Decision Making
- Just Cause c.1991 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  Excerpts from unknown book re seven tests of just cause in employee discipline cases
- Kentucky Ed. Reform 1990-1993 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  A Guide to the Kentucky Reform Act of 1990, Legislative Research Commission; The Kentucky Education Reform Act of 1990: A Citizen's Handbook, Legislative Research Commission, revised September 1991; "Finding Time for School Reform: Obstacles and Answers," a joint study by the Kentucky Education Association and Appalachia Educational Laboratory, funded in part by the U.S. Department of Education, March 1993; SEEK: Support Education Excellence in Kentucky: Public School Finance in Kentucky, 1993; related documents
- Labor History 1981 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  Anti-union cartoons by the National Association of Manufacturers; "A Short History of American Labor," reprint of AFL-CIO American Federationist, March 1981; "American Labor: A Bicentennial History," by M.B. Schnapper, compilation of early twentieth-century newspaper articles re child labor, women's labor
- Labor's Bill of Rights 1988-1993 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  Remarks by Paul F. Cole, secretary-treasurer, NYS AFL-CIO, at Conversations with History, November 3, 1988; program for Conversations with History 50th anniversary forum of the 1938 NYS constitutional convention; labor history month article for PERB News by Harold R. Newman, with cover letter from author to NYSUT president Hobart, June 14, 1993
- Landrum-Griffin Act c. 1969 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  Summary of provision of Landrum-Griffin Act with which NYSUT must comply
- Language Other Than English (LOTE) (Foreign Language Requirement) 1999 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  State Education Department discussion item re accommodations for late arriving students with limited English language proficiency at the secondary level, June 25, 1999; discussion item, results of survey on recommendations of Foreign language Implementation Committee, January 11, 1999. See also: Foreign Language
- LAPP Grants. See: Local Action Pilot Project/Program
- Latino Issues, Task Force on (AFT) 2004 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  Summary report, correspondence
- Leadership Development 1987 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  Notes from brainstorming session of new subcommittee of Administrative Committee to explore ways in which NYSUT can ensure leadership continuity among local presidents; committee members were Tony Bifaro, assistant to President Hobart, Chuck Santelli, director of research and educational services, and Jim Conti, director of field services
- Leadership Institute, Nomination Forms 2003 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  Applications by district for Cornell ILR-NYSUT Leadership Institute
- League for Industrial Democracy 1993-1994 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  Brochures, "The Role of Black Trade Unions in Fostering Integration," presentation by Norman Hill to the Jewish Labor Committee, February 15, 1994; "Labor and Society: A Roundtable Discussion on Catholic Social Thought with Thomas R. Donahue, John T. Joyce, Michael Novak, George Weigel," League for Industrial Democracy, n.d.; League for Industrial Democracy, 1994 program summary; 1992-93 program summary, with cover letter; "Why America Needs a Social Democratic Movement: A Statement on Our Economy, Our Polity and Our Community," Social Democrats, USA, August 1993
- Learning First Alliance 2/13-14/03, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  Meeting materials, including agenda, update on state alliances; proposed governance revisions; bylaws and constitution; September minutes; financial statements; selected articles re purposes of public education; presentation, "Getting and Keeping Talented Teachers: A National Overview," Council of Chief State School Officers, December 15, 2003; brochure for Center on Education Policy; correspondence
- Learning First Alliance 9/12/2002 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  Materials for board meeting, including agenda, audit materials (memo from finance chair, fiscal year 2003 audit and audit report), financial statements; May minutes; cross-case analysis of cost-effective professional practices
- Learning First Alliance. Forum of Educational Organization Leaders 1/23-24/2001 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  Meeting materials, including agenda; minutes of September 2000 meeting; "Every Child Reading: A Professional Development Guide"; overview and future directions; press release, "New Agreement Reached on Guidelines for Teaching Reading: Alliance Unites National Education Groups to Promote What Works for Professional Development," December 6, 2000
- Learning First Alliance (folder 1 of 2) 9/12/00, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  Meeting materials, including agenda; activity updates (executive director's report, finance committee report); High Stakes Assessment discussion; National School Boards Association's Student Achievement Institute; initiative on professional practice; presentation on National Commission on Mathematics and Science Teaching for the 21st Century; cover letter explaining packet contents
- Learning First Alliance (folder 2 of 2) 9/12/00, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  Meeting materials, including agenda; executive director's report; discussion of state alliances; national reading panel report; new NCTM (National Council of Teachers of Mathematics) standards
- Learning First Alliance 5/23-24/00, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  Meeting materials, including agenda; January minutes; memo re future directions of the alliance; briefing paper on alliances' state partnerships; statement of goals; draft action plan on safe and supportive learning communities; list of board members and bios; correspondence
- Learning First Alliance 1/18/00, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  Meeting materials, including agenda; report on strengthening professional practice: state actions in five key areas; statement of commitment by chief state school officers; related documents
- Learning First Alliance 5/10-11/1999 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  Meeting materials, including agenda; January minutes; Kauffman grant summary; mathematics public engagement campaign; press release and related materials for Achieve, Inc., press conference
- Learning First Alliance 1/7-8/99, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  Meeting materials, including agenda; statement of auditors; proposal for follow-up on "Every Child Reading"; description of Reading Excellence Act; memo to Learning First Public Relations Task Force re media mailings to top education writers by Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development
- Learning First Alliance 6/15/98, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  Meeting materials, including agenda; history of Learning First Alliance as outgrowth of Forum of Educational Organizations; minutes of April meeting; brochure for National Partnership for Excellence and Accountability in Teaching; working drafts of action plans to improve reading and mathematics learning, April 27, 1998; related correspondence
- Learning First Alliance. Forum of Educational Organization Leaders 1997 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Agenda; September minutes; outline of reading and math action papers
- Learning Styles 1987-1988 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  State Education Department publication, "Increasing High School Completion Rates: A Framework for State and Local and Action," July 1987; draft research on leaning styles by Richard Harned, SUNY Buffalo, Kenmore Teachers Association, Tonawanda, AFT Research and Dissemination Program, n.d.; article re controversial statements re black learning styles by Edmund Gordon, chair of State Education Department symposium panel to study an also-controversial handbook on dropouts, 1988; transcript of remarks at symposium; paper presented at symposium; handwritten notes
- Legal (NYSUT ) 1989 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  Drafts of amendments to NYS Education Law re professional mediation, professional decision-making, with cover memo to vp Cortese, soliciting comments
- LEGAL REVIEW 1991-2005 (Box 11)
  Correspondence re cases of individual teachers represented (or denied representation) by NYSUT Legal Review Committee in termination and other disputes
  - Michael Davey. Greenburgh No. 11 Federation of Teachers 12/17/91, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 3 East Syracuse-Minoa 1992 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 4 Loraine Fusco. East Quogue1992 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 5 Clifford Lehman. Christian Brothers Academy 1995 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - 6 Carol Maddox. Ossining 1989 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - 7 Rhoda Dreifuss. Lynbrook (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 8 Loren Boland. Onondaga-Cortland-Madison BOCES 1991 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - 9 Ron Peritti 2005 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - 10 Donald Pomeroy. Plattsburgh 1995 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - 11 Patchogue/Medford Congress of Teachers 1995 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - 12 Sheila Salenger. Wappingers Congress of Teachers 1992 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - 13 Barbara Pisarek. Wappingers Congress of Teachers 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - 14 Arnold Sabino. King's Park Classroom Teachers Association 1998 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - 15 Orchard Park 1999 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - 16 James Buffoni. Indian River Education Association 1992 (Box 11, Folder 18)